An investor selling a
Put Option receives
a fixed premium and gives
another investor the right,
but not the obligation,
to sell an asset at
a predetermined price,
until expiration.
A short put strategy
might be considered by
a risk-tolerant trader with
the opinion that a stock's price,
is likely to increase and
or volatility is
likely to decrease.
The put seller benefits from
the passage of time and
the decreasing dividends.
The maximum gain is
the premium received,
which occurs at any price
above the strike price.
The gain diminishes
as the price of the
underlying falls below
the strike price.
Break-even occurs at the sum of
the strike price less
the premium received.
Any price below that,
the short put seller
begins to lose money,
penny for penny, as the
underlying price decreases.
Loss potential is substantial.
Short put sellers must
ensure that they are
sufficiently capitalized to
deliver any required shares.